- [Narrator] This is a Formula
One pit stop in real time.
(machine whirring)
Within just two and a half seconds,
all four tires are changed
and even the car setup was modified.
And to understand how that is possible,
I've animated the entire thing
so we can take a look
at it in slow motion.
(upbeat music)
The first factor determining
the speed of the stop is
how well the driver manages
getting into the pits.
Every pit lane has a strict speed limit.
On tracks with particularly
tight or short layouts
like Monaco, the speed is
capped at 60 kilometers an hour,
but on most circuits
it's 80 or about 50 MPH.
In order to lose little time,
the driver tries to break
as late as possible when
entering the pit lane.
Once past this line,
the driver presses a dedicated
button on the steering wheel
that locks the car to the speed limit.
Next, the driver turns into the box
and has to place the car
as precise as possible
as the entire pit crew is
positioned with pinpoint accuracy.
If the driver overshoots even slightly,
the whole team has to adjust,
stepping forward to compensate
and wasting valuable time.
To help the driver nail their mark,
teams use a mechanical arm
with an arrow in the pit box
and the perfect stop
happens when the front tires
line up exactly beneath that arrow.
One of the boldest roles in the pit crew
belongs to the front jack operator.
This person stands directly
in front of the car,
positioning the front jack
so that it catches just a bit of momentum
from the nose cone as
the car comes to a halt.
Then in once move motion,
the operator lifts the car from the front.
At the same time, behind the car,
the rear jack operator gets into position.
Since they need to leave
room for the car to enter,
they're slightly slower
than the front jack,
but the moment the car stops,
they also slide a jack into
place lifting the back wheels.
Meanwhile, on either side of the car,
two stabilizers step in.
Their job is to absorb the
sudden jolts from lifting,
making sure it's perfectly
aligned for the stop.
For changing the actual tires,
the wheel change crew
consists of 12 people,
three for each tire.
At the center of each team
is the person holding the wheel gun.
Even before the car stops,
this person is tracking its
movement aligning themselves
so they can instantly
lock onto the wheel knot
and apply torque the
moment they get a chance.
Unlike regular car wheels,
which are typically fastened
with five bolts, an F1 tire is secured
with just one single lock
knot precision manufactured
with multiple poles that
the wheel gun can lock onto.
The wheel guns themselves are
custom made for this purpose
and require immense strength to operate.
That is because they can
spin at up to 15,000 RPM
enough force to rip it
right out of your hands
if you aren't ready for it.
Since a couple of years,
the front of each wheel
gun features an LED ring
that shows the real-time
status to the operator.
The exact color coding
varies from team to team,
but in our example, the gun
initially glows white indicating
that it is in loosening mode.
As soon as the tire is loose
and the gunman releases the trigger,
the wheel gun then
automatically switches its mode.
The LED changes from white to blue,
and the gun has entered
its tightening mode,
meaning the next time
the trigger is pulled,
it will spin in the opposite direction.
(dramatic music)
As this is happening, the
person in front of the tire
quickly moves it aside, and
in perfect synchronization,
the person behind is bringing
the fresh tire into position
so that the wheel gun operator
can begin tightening it.
The wheel gun automatically detects
when the wheel is fully secured
and the LED ring now lights up green.
As soon as that happens,
the gunman presses a button on the gun
sending an electronic confirmation
that their task is complete.
While all of this is unfolding,
the front jack operator
has already stepped aside
to clear the space for the car's release.
The jack is designed to
keep the car lifted up
while it swivels out of place,
and once they're in a safe position,
the jack operator presses
a button on the jack
to confirm they're also ready.
Each of these button
presses serves one purpose,
to ensure that every key function
signals when they're done.
(dramatic music)
The driver in the meantime
isn't watching the crew.
They are focused on a traffic
light in front of them,
and until every single crew
member has pressed their button,
it will remain red.
Because while the front tires are done,
the rears still need to be secured.
These often take slightly
longer to finish simply
because the rear jack lifts the car
a fraction of a second
later than the front jack.
And on top of that, the
rear tires are larger
and heavier than the front ones,
making them a bit trickier to handle.
Sometimes a driver will
have radioed in a message
that they'd like their front wing
to be adjusted during the stop.
If that is the case, two mechanics step in
from the front of the car,
each carrying a
pre-programmed torque driver,
they insert it into designated
holes on the front wing,
and the torque driver rotates a screw
by a precise number of turns
adjusting the angle of the front wing,
which changes to car's aerodynamics.
(dramatic music)
Just as these adjustments are done,
the rear tires are also secured.
All four gunmen have signaled they're done
and the front jack operator
has given the all clear,
but for safety reasons,
the light doesn't switch
to green automatically.
Instead, the crew chief
who oversees everything,
provides the final confirmation.
Only when all has gone to plan
and when the pit lane is clear
with no other cars blocking the exit,
does the crew chief press the button.
The front jack drops the
car, the light turns green,
and the car takes off.
(rocking music)
All that in just two and a half seconds.
(gentle music)
In Formula One, clear communication
can make or break a race.
And the same is also true in aviation.
And what happens when
communication goes bad
is what I explore in my full length video
about the Tenerife Disaster.
(gentle music)
The video tells the story
of how in 1977, 2 Boeing 747s collided
with each other on a runway.
It is to this day the worst
accident in aviation history,
and it was one of my most
ambitious videos I ever worked on.
This video is part of my
documentary series "Under Exposure"
a series where I bring
fascinating stories to light
that I believe deserved to be told.
For example, I made a video
about two East German families
that fled their country with nothing
but a homemade hot air balloon
attempting the daring escape
of flying over the heavily
guarded border at night.
And for this video, I
even got to interview
one of the people involved.
The reason I was able to
make all these videos is
because I joined forces with
a bunch of other creators,
and together we are building Nebula.
The idea is pretty simple.
Since Nebula is not an
ad-driven platform like YouTube,
but a subscription model,
we get to create higher
budget productions.
And besides my own series,
we also have game shows,
incredible documentaries, short films,
and even full length feature films.
Plus I always post my videos there early,
so you can already watch
my next upload there today.
So go to nebula.tv/neo
and make sure to use exactly this link
in order to get 40% of the annual plan.
So thanks for the support
and thank you so much
for watching this video.